<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linked Data on Newres Al Haider</title>
    <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/linked-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linked Data on Newres Al Haider</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Newres Al Haider</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/linked-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Aesopica, Part 4: Basic Conversion to Other Formats</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-4/</guid>
      <description>This article is the fourth part of a series, examining the use of the Clojure language for representing Linked Data, with examples from Aesop&amp;rsquo;s stories. The topic of this article is to describe how to do some basic conversions from our Clojure representation of Linked Data, to some of the other formats, such as Turtle, NQUADS or JSON-LD.
In previous articles of this series, we created a Clojure based syntax for defining Linked Data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aesopica, Part 3: Named Graphs</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-3/</guid>
      <description>This article is the third part of a series, examining the use of the Clojure language for representing Linked Data, with examples from Aesop&amp;rsquo;s stories. In part one the basic elements of &amp;ldquo;The Fox and the Stork&amp;rdquo; story were formalised as Linked Data in Clojure, while in part two we investigated how various literal values can be described. In this article we examine how information about facts themselves, such as meta-information, can be described with Linked Data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aesopica, Part 2: Literal Values</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-2/</guid>
      <description>This article is the second part of a series, examining the use of the Clojure language for representing Linked Data, with examples from Aesop&amp;rsquo;s stories. Part one can be found on this site where the basic elements of the Fox and the Stork story were formalised. In this article we examine how literal values can be represented, using Clojure, in Linked Data. The code to enable the functionality described in these articles can be found in the Aesopica library for using Clojure to write Linked Data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aesopica, Part 1: General Introduction</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-1/</guid>
      <description>The stories called Aesop&amp;rsquo;s Fables or the Aesopica, are an ancient collection of stories that have been passed down to modern day. These stories are of diverse origins they cover a wide variety of themes. Although originally intended for an adult audience, in later times were often used for the education of children.
One of such stories is the tale of the Fox and the Stork. There are many versions of this fable, but the overall outline is generally as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Interlinked</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/interlinked-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/interlinked-data/</guid>
      <description>This article contains some very minor spoilers for the Blade Runner 2049 movie. If you have not seen it yet, by all means do, it is really good.
&amp;ldquo;And blood-black nothingness began to spin&amp;hellip; A system of cells interlinked within cells interlinked within cells interlinked within one stem&amp;hellip; And dreadfully distinct against the dark, a tall white fountain played.&amp;rdquo;
  Pale Fire by Vladimir Nabokov  Cover of the novel Pale Fire © Berkley Medallion   The above is a quote from the poem Pale Fire.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>