<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Semantic Web on Newres Al Haider</title>
    <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/semantic-web/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Semantic Web on Newres Al Haider</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Newres Al Haider</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/semantic-web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Aesopica: part 1</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-1/</guid>
      <description>The stories called Aesop&amp;rsquo;s Fables or the Aesopica, are an ancient collection of stories that have been passed down to modern day. These stories are of diverse origins they cover a wide variety of themes. Although originally intended for an adult audience, in later times were often used for the education of children.
One of such stories is the tale of the Fox and the Stork. There are many versions of this fable, but the overall outline is generally as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Interlinked</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/interlinked-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/interlinked-data/</guid>
      <description>This article contains some very minor spoilers for the Blade Runner 2049 movie. If you have not seen it yet, by all means do, it is really good.
&amp;ldquo;And blood-black nothingness began to spin&amp;hellip; A system of cells interlinked within cells interlinked within cells interlinked within one stem&amp;hellip; And dreadfully distinct against the dark, a tall white fountain played.&amp;rdquo;
  Pale Fire by Vladimir Nabokov  Cover of the novel Pale Fire © Berkley Medallion   The above is a quote from the poem Pale Fire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legal Regulatory Compliance Within The Financial Domain.</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/legal-banking-compliance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/legal-banking-compliance/</guid>
      <description>Regulatory compliance is the goal of an organization to ensure it complies with all the relevant policies, regulations and laws. Failure to comply can have grave consequences for an organization, with huge fines and penalties being imposed. Regulatory pressure has been increasing over the years, with new and more complex regulation being enacted. This is especially true for the financial sector, where in the wake of the financial crisis, new policies and laws where enacted, both internal and external, to prevent a similar crisis happening in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ontology Enabled Clinical Software</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/clinical-semantics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/clinical-semantics/</guid>
      <description>The time of clinical health professionals is incredibly valuable. Software can alleviate the burden of physicians, nursers and other health experts and allow them to provide better, more effective health care to patients.
Creating, maintaining and using software in clinical environments is a difficult process. Not only it is paramount that such software needs to be correct, it has to have an understanding of highly domain specific knowledge about clinical processes in order to provide beneficial support to health professionals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Aware Software Analysis</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/semantic-software-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/semantic-software-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Software bugs and errors have a monumental negative impact on society. Not only can they have huge monetary cost, ranging into billions of dollars annually in the United States alone, but in some cases can even lead to disasters that lead to the loss of life. Preventing such issues from happening requires a large amount of effort in designing and maintaining software.
However designing and maintaining error free software remains a difficult problem.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>