<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prolog on Newres Al Haider</title>
    <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/prolog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Prolog on Newres Al Haider</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Newres Al Haider</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/prolog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Probable Mystery Machine</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/probable-mystery-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/probable-mystery-machine/</guid>
      <description>Scooby Doo is mystery horror cartoon series in which a group of teenagers named Fred, Daphne, Velma and Shaggy alongside the titular Great Dane named Scooby-Doo, ride around in their van named &amp;ldquo;The Mystery Machine&amp;rdquo; solving mysteries. The episodes of the show generally follow a set structure. First their van tends to break down near a place apparently haunted by a ghost or another supernatural creature. They would offer to solve the mystery behind the existence of the monster and start looking for clues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prolog and the Price of Peace</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/prolog-price-of-peace/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/prolog-price-of-peace/</guid>
      <description>The use of logic is a common element in Science Fiction. In the Star Trek universe Vulcans are a species that is famously known for aiming to live by logic and reason. Because of this they are often considered masters of these subjects. Yet there was a case in an episode of the Star Trek show Deep Space 9, where Quark, a Ferengi, was able to convince Sakonna, a Vulcan, of the error of her logic and reasoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Choosing a Programming Language</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/art-of-choosing-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/art-of-choosing-language/</guid>
      <description>Programmers, like professionals in other fields, are passionate about their tools. One of the main elements in the toolbox of coders are programming languages. They allow their users to express solutions through code to tackle a large variety of problems in many domains.
Programming is also an art, as described in the article by Donald Knuth titled Computer Programming as an Art and in certain aspects of programming languages can be seen as art styles.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>