<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Knowledge representation on Newres Al Haider</title>
    <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/knowledge-representation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Knowledge representation on Newres Al Haider</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Newres Al Haider</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/knowledge-representation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Aesopica: part 2</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-2/</guid>
      <description>This article is the second part of a series, examining the use of the Clojure language for representing Linked Data, with examples from Aesop&amp;rsquo;s stories. Part one can be found on this site where the basic elements of the Fox and the Stork story were formalised. In this article we examine how literal values can be represented, using Clojure, in Linked Data. The code to enable the functionality described in these articles can be found in the Aesopica library for using Clojure to write Linked Data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aesopica: part 1</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/aesopica-1/</guid>
      <description>The stories called Aesop&amp;rsquo;s Fables or the Aesopica, are an ancient collection of stories that have been passed down to modern day. These stories are of diverse origins they cover a wide variety of themes. Although originally intended for an adult audience, in later times were often used for the education of children.
One of such stories is the tale of the Fox and the Stork. There are many versions of this fable, but the overall outline is generally as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Excavating a Common Treasure</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/common-treasure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/common-treasure/</guid>
      <description>History is full of legends of ancient treasures and powerful artifacts, lost to time or hidden by purpose, that would bring glory, power and riches to their discoverer.
  A winged bull depicted on an on archaeological artifact from the Assyrian empire between 1400 and 1200 BC. Cylinder Seal with Winged Bull - Walters Art Museum Licensed under CC0.   Although the history of software development is much shorter than the history of mankind, there already exists artifacts that have near mythological status when it comes to software development, yet often go hidden underneath the surface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spec-stacular Spider-Man</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/spec-stacular-spider-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/spec-stacular-spider-man/</guid>
      <description>Spider-Man is one of the most iconic heroes of the Marvel universe. Created by Stan Lee and Steve Ditko, Spider-Man is a regular teenager named Peter Parker, who due to being bitten by a radio-active spider, gains abilities such as the proportional strength of a spider, wall crawling and a spider sense to detect upcoming danger. One of the biggest draws of Spider-Man that although he is a superhero and fought various villains from cosmic beings to petty criminals, he also had to deal with regular everyday problems, such as money issues, school life and the pressure of a job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Interlinked</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/interlinked-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/interlinked-data/</guid>
      <description>This article contains some very minor spoilers for the Blade Runner 2049 movie. If you have not seen it yet, by all means do, it is really good.
&amp;ldquo;And blood-black nothingness began to spin&amp;hellip; A system of cells interlinked within cells interlinked within cells interlinked within one stem&amp;hellip; And dreadfully distinct against the dark, a tall white fountain played.&amp;rdquo;
  Pale Fire by Vladimir Nabokov  Cover of the novel Pale Fire © Berkley Medallion   The above is a quote from the poem Pale Fire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Trouble with Triples</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/trouble-with-triples/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/trouble-with-triples/</guid>
      <description>In the Star Trek episode &amp;ldquo;The Trouble with Tribbles&amp;rdquo; the crew of the starship Enterprise encounters creatures called Tribbles. They are cute, simple creatures of mysterious origin that seem harmless at first but when they multiply the pose a big problem for the ship and the crew.
  Tribbles  Tribbles © 1967 Paramount Pictures   Representing and reasoning with knowledge have surprisingly similar problems. A single fact on its own is a relatively straightforward affair.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/introduction/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first post on my blog on which hopefully many will follow. My intention is to write about knowledge representation, reasoning, AI and coding, in an easily digestible but in depth-way.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>