<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title> - Law</title>
	<link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/law/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2022-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://www.newresalhaider.com/tags/law/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Data Oriented Domain Design</title>
		<published>2022-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/dodd/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/dodd/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most difficult parts of developing software for a particular task is understanding the (business) domain in which the software needs to operate. This is due to the fact that software engineers often lack the expertise in complex areas such as health, law, finance, etc in which the software they create needs to solve problems. A similar situation holds for domain experts. For example, while lawyers are by definition well versed in the legal domain, it is not necessarily the case that they are also software engineers. This lack of knowledge can make developing software quite difficult. To continue with our legal example, suppose we want to create an application that represents and searches laws. From the software engineers side, the legal terminology can be quite burdensome to understand and it might not be very clear to them what aspects of it would be important for them to implement. On the other hand, it is important to be able to make it understandable to legal experts, without any software engineering knowledge, what the software is doing in relation to the concepts in their domain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various solutions have been proposed for this problem, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Domain-driven_design&quot;&gt;Domain Driven Design&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and formalizing the domain using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.w3.org&#x2F;standards&#x2F;semanticweb&#x2F;ontology&quot;&gt;Linked Data Ontologies&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
These methodologies can be quite complex, which they need to be in order to capture the nuances of the domain and descriptions of what is possible. This makes the important process of domain formalisation often quite daunting. In this article, I will show a very lightweight approach, that can be applied as a starting point towards formalising the domain. The core idea is to use lightweight data notation languages, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.json.org&#x2F;json-en.html&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;edn-format&#x2F;edn&quot;&gt;EDN&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to represent elements of the domain. The elements of these languages, such as the notations for sequences, key and value pairs, etc would then be used as a common language for both the software engineer and domain expert to explain the problem and how the software is used to solve it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of this article I will call this method Data Oriented Domain Design (DODD). Not coincidentally the subject that we aim to represent are a few elements of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.congress.gov&#x2F;bill&#x2F;111th-congress&#x2F;house-bill&#x2F;4173&#x2F;text?r=1&quot;&gt;Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which we will simply refer as the Dodd-Frank law in this context. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I will make use of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;edn-format&#x2F;edn&quot;&gt;EDN&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;(Extensible Data Notation) data notation language to illustrate the ideas of this Data Oriented Domain Design (DODD). EDN is a language where information is represented through a set of elements as values. The elements are common to many programming languages. For example here are elements for representing text, time, numbers as well as collections, such as lists, sets, etc. of these elements. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDN is a subset of the programming language &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. A large part of a Clojure program is manipulating information expressed in EDN. Due to this reason Clojure is often called a data-oriented or data-driven language. With Data Oriented Domain Design we are going to use this &amp;quot;data orientation paradigm&amp;quot; not just for organizing the software system but also for creating a common language in which software engineers and domain experts can communicate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to make things more concrete lets imagine a scenario where small application is needed to be built that aims to search for definitions within legal documents. One of the nice aspects of many legal texts is that they often have a section of definitions that the reader can refer to. Our application will aim to retrieve these definitions based on a given criteria. As an example use case, given the acronym DODD of our approach, we will use the text of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.congress.gov&#x2F;bill&#x2F;111th-congress&#x2F;house-bill&#x2F;4173&#x2F;text?r=1&quot;&gt;Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which we will simply refer as the Dodd-Frank law in this context. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to preface this by saying that &amp;quot;I am not a lawyer&amp;quot; and I am looking at this application from a software- and knowledge engineers perspective. I will simplify out a LOT of the intricacies of legal text search and representation. That said as mentioned this perspective should be illustrative of the issues when developing software for such a new domain and how Data Oriented Domain Design could be a good starting point.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text of this law has multiple sections for definitions, but here in particular we are looking at the first ten definitions outlined in Section 2 of the Dodd-Frank act. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;SEC. 2. &amp;lt;&amp;lt;NOTE: 12 USC 5301.&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DEFINITIONS.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    As used in this Act, the following definitions shall apply, except 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;as the context otherwise requires or as otherwise specifically provided 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;in this Act:
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (1) Affiliate.--The term ``affiliate&amp;#39;&amp;#39; has the same meaning 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        as in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (12 U.S.C. 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        1813).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (2) Appropriate federal banking agency.--On and after the 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        transfer date, the term ``appropriate Federal banking agency&amp;#39;&amp;#39; 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        has the same meaning as in section 3(q) of the Federal Deposit 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Insurance Act (12 U.S.C. 1813(q)), as amended by title III.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[[Page 124 STAT. 1387]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (3) Board of governors.--The term ``Board of Governors&amp;#39;&amp;#39; 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (4) Bureau.--The term ``Bureau&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Bureau of 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Consumer Financial Protection established under title X.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (5) Commission.--The term ``Commission&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Securities and Exchange Commission, except in the context of the 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Commodity Futures Trading Commission.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (6) Commodity futures terms.--The terms ``futures commission 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        merchant&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, ``swap&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, ``swap dealer&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, ``swap execution 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        facility&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, ``derivatives clearing organization&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, ``board of 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        trade&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, ``commodity trading advisor&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, ``commodity pool&amp;#39;&amp;#39;, and 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        ``commodity pool operator&amp;#39;&amp;#39; have the same meanings as given the 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        terms in section 1a of the Commodity Exchange Act (7 U.S.C. 1 et 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        seq.).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (7) Corporation.--The term ``Corporation&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Federal 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Deposit Insurance Corporation.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (8) Council.--The term ``Council&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Financial 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Stability Oversight Council established under title I.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (9) Credit union.--The term ``credit union&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means a Federal 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        credit union, State credit union, or State-chartered credit 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        union, as those terms are defined in section 101 of the Federal 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Credit Union Act (12 U.S.C. 1752).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            (10) Federal banking agency.--The term--
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                    (A) ``Federal banking agency&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means, individually, 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                the Board of Governors, the Office of the Comptroller of 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                the Currency, and the Corporation; and
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                    (B) ``Federal banking agencies&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means all of the 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                agencies referred to in subparagraph (A), collectively.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now lets consider the case of an application searching for definitions in legal text. One of the features we would like to do is that given the exact name of the term, such as &amp;quot;Board of Governors&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Bureau&amp;quot;, etc, the text of its definition is found. The name of the term can be represented as data with a string of characters. In Clojure, and many other languages, this is denoted as the text between quotation marks (&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). For example, the input for our search can be given as:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Board of Governors&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we have to examine on how to represent the output (the result) of our search. In most cases we would like to have a sequence of results that indicate the found definitions. This is due to a number of reasons. First, a specific term could be defined with multiple definitions over a variety of documents. Second, it provides us a straightforward way to represent the results in the case when there are no results are found. In this case we can return an indicator of a sequence of 0 elements. In Clojure such a sequence of elements can be indicated by elements in between square brackets &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Other data interchange formats and languages call such ordered sequence by different terms: lists, arrays, etc. Such representations are very common in (programming languages) but for in this article we will stick with the EDN definitions. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our first version of our program we will just return the sequence of the found texts that describes the definition. To give a concrete example lets assume we search for the term &amp;quot;Board of Governors&amp;quot; in the above partial document. The input for our program is the string of characters indicating this term:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Board of Governors&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the output would be:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[ &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(3) Board of governors.--The term ``Board of Governors&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To show an example where we would not find any definitions in the above text, if we search for the term &amp;quot;Central Bank&amp;quot; in the above fragment using the input&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Central Bank&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we would get an empty sequence as a result:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving examples such as this should already give a good indication on how the code could be structured. Just as importantly, given some information on the basic notation of sequences and strings, legal domain experts could understand the program is aiming to achieve, just by looking at a few of such examples and verify whether we are on the right track.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the above example is a very minimal abstraction. Let&#x27;s try to expand upon it, to capture a few more elements of the legal domain. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The location in which the searched terms are found is also quite important. A program might search legal terms over multiple legal documents, and if found, people would likely want to know exact location in the source material to get more context. This means that we want to represent a few additional values in our search result. For example if the definition was found in a law, we would also want to have the title of the law, the section in which the definition was found, the URL of where the law could be read, etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In EDN the format to represent such key-value pairs is called map, represented by pairs of elements between curly brackets: &lt;code&gt;{}&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. For example if we want to express the term description with a key-value pair, with both the key and value being a string, we could write:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[{ &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;description&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(3) Board of governors.--The term ``Board of Governors&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;}]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other languages such maps are called as object, record, struct, dictionary, hash table, etc but the general concept is the same. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main question is of-course what additional elements we want add here and what we would like to name the keys of these elements. To reiterate, &amp;quot;I am not a Lawyer&amp;quot;, but we can look towards the ways of how laws are cited to figure out what additional information would make sense from a legal perspective. Thankfully there are some descriptions online on how to cite laws, such on the site of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;guides.libraries.uc.edu&#x2F;c.php?g=222561&amp;amp;p=1472889&quot;&gt;University of Cincinnati&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.law.cornell.edu&#x2F;citation&#x2F;2-300&quot;&gt;Cornell University Law&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this information, we will add the terms &amp;quot;title of the act&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;public law number&amp;quot; &amp;quot;statute&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;year of enaction&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;url&amp;quot; of the law where this definition was found to our search result. Below is the expanded example:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[{ &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;description&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(3) Board of governors.--The term ``Board of Governors&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;title-of-act&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;H.R.4173 - Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;public-law-number&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;111-203&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;statute&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;1387&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;year-of-enaction&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;2010&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;url&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.congress.gov&#x2F;bill&#x2F;111th-congress&#x2F;house-bill&#x2F;4173&#x2F;text?r=1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;}]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this might be sufficient, but again there are some features we could use to make this a better representation. First, we use a lot of strings of characters when we ideally want to specify a number or numbers. In EDN, as well as in JSON and other formats, you generally have a bit more precision and safety by expressing these elements as numbers (or more precisely integers). By the program that we intend to build, this helps us automatically invalidate certain wrong values and helps us better describe the intent of what is allowed. For example if we write the string &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;start&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; instead of a number such as &#x27;111&#x27; for the law number, this program should handle this by not allowing such scenaros to occur that contradict the rules of the domain. The extra precision allows us to more precisely declare the range of laws, with a number denoting the starting and the ending point with the keys &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;from&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;to&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[{ &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;description&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(3) Board of governors.--The term ``Board of Governors&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;title-of-act&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;H.R.4173 - Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;public-law-number&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; {&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;from&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;111 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;to&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;203&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;} 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;statute&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;1387&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;year-of-enaction&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;2010
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;url&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.congress.gov&#x2F;bill&#x2F;111th-congress&#x2F;house-bill&#x2F;4173&#x2F;text?r=1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;}]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are going to add one additional feature to improve this representation. Note that depending on what we search for, certain the strings representing the values will vary a lot while those for the keys will remain the same. For example the value for the returned description can be &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;(3) Board of governors.--The term ``Board of Governors&#x27;&#x27; means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; if we search for the term &amp;quot;Board of governors&amp;quot;, while it will be &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;(4) Bureau.--The term ``Bureau&#x27;&#x27; means the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection established under title X.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; if we search for &amp;quot;Bureau&amp;quot;. However the key for both of these values would be &amp;quot;description&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution in EDN is to use keywords, for the commonly used strings. The names of these are prefaced by &lt;code&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; instead of putting them in quotation marks. While JSON does not have such keywords, many other languages do. Notably &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;json-ld.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;JSON-LD&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; can use &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Uniform_Resource_Identifier&quot;&gt;Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for a similar purpose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using keywords we can give an output for our definition search as follows:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-clojure &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[{ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;:description &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(3) Board of governors.--The term ``Board of Governors&amp;#39;&amp;#39; means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;:title-of-act &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;H.R.4173 - Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;:public-law-number&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt; {&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;from&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;: 111 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;to&amp;quot;&amp;quot;: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;203&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;} 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;:statute&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1387&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;  :year-of-enaction 2010
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;  :url &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.congress.gov&#x2F;bill&#x2F;111th-congress&#x2F;house-bill&#x2F;4173&#x2F;text?r=1&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;}]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one can see from just these few examples there can be quite a few ways in which domain concepts are represented. A small set of examples, that describe the elements of the domain in a way that is understandable for both the domain expert and the software engineer can be invaluable. The great benefit of Data Oriented Domain Design, is that it co-opts some battle tested light-weight data representation languages, such as EDN, for this purpose. This allows for some excellent test cases to use when developing the software with methodologies such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Test-driven_development&quot;&gt;Test Driven Development (TDD)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- [JSON-LD](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;json-ld.org&#x2F;)  --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the above approach has some limitations. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A notation such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;json-ld.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;JSON-LD&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; can be more expressive with representing the domain and is more capable of representing linked data (i.e.: data that is interconnected with other data). However starting to model the domain with explicit links to other data sources can be more complex especially in cases where domain experts formalize the domain for the first time. As JSON-LD is designed to provide a smooth upgrade path from JSON, starting out with a pure JSON based modelling of the domain can be a great initial step.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DODD also explains the domain through a set of examples, but not through a comprehensive set of restrictions that model the domain in a more complete way. However there exist schema languages, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.org&#x2F;guides&#x2F;spec&quot;&gt;Clojure Spec&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Web_Ontology_Language&quot;&gt;OWL Ontologies&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that can model more of such restrictions, and could extend validation a lot further.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue is that these lightweight data languages are often designed for the perspective of a software engineer, that most likely is going to utilize them. However with some tooling they could be made more accessible with domain experts, especially as they are relatively straightforward, with fewer elements, compared to more complex representations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless even with these limitations, Data Oriented Domain Design in which a lightweight data notation language is used to help express examples of a domain to both domain experts and software engineers, can provide a relatively gentle start to modelling the domain through a set of examples. Due to its relative simplicity it could be applied as an initial step, before more &amp;quot;heavyweight&amp;quot; models are brought into the picture. It can provide a great tool for some frank discussions on how a software should function in a particular domain. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Prolog and the Price of Peace</title>
		<published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2019-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/prolog-price-of-peace/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/prolog-price-of-peace/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The use of logic is a common element in Science Fiction. In the Star Trek universe &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Vulcan_(Star_Trek)&quot;&gt;Vulcans&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are a species that is famously known for aiming to live by logic and reason. Because of this they are often considered masters of these subjects. Yet there was a case in an episode of the Star Trek show &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;memory-alpha.wikia.com&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;The_Maquis,_Part_II_(episode)&quot;&gt;Deep Space 9&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, where &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Quark_(Star_Trek)&quot;&gt;Quark&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Ferengi&quot;&gt;Ferengi&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, was able to convince Sakonna, a Vulcan, of the error of her logic and reasoning. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this Quark made use of Ferengi philosophy, namely the Third Rule of Acquisition. The Rules of Acquisition are a series of proverbs and guidelines that govern Ferengi society, and notably their business dealings that take a prominent place in their lives. The Third Rule of Acquisition states that &amp;quot;Never spend more for an acquisition than you have to.&amp;quot; By applying this rule to the situation in the episode Quark was able make it clear to Sakonna that the best time broker a peace agreement would be &amp;quot;right now&amp;quot;, as the price of peace is at an all time low. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;featured.jpg&quot;  &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;Quark explaining the Third Rule of Acquisition to Sakonna Copyright CBS Corporation.&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
  &lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;!-- {{&lt; figure src=&quot;featured.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Quark explaining the Third Rule of Acquisition to Sakonna&quot; attr=&quot;Copyright CBS Corporation&quot; &gt;}} --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like with Ferengi society, various rules and regulations play a prominent role in our lives and dealings with each other. So much so, that navigating the various rules to their logical conclusion, whether in the realm of law, finance and other domains, is often a difficult process. Thankfully there are tools and techniques to help us. The programming language Prolog, in particular, can be a very helpful in dealing with various rules and logical problems. This article aims to provide a brief introduction to this language using by using it to show how Quark&#x27;s reasoning can be implemented within a computer program.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prolog is a logic programming language, originally created in the 1970s, but with many modern implementations such as &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.swi-prolog.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;SWI-Prolog&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. With logic programming programs are written and solved using some variation of a formal logic. Using such logic, information about the problem and its domain is first declared. Then the user can pose queries about the problem domain, which the programming language aims to answer through reasoning with the available information. This style of programming contrasts with the more common, imperative, paradigm. Instead of telling the computer how to solve the problem, we can declare information about the problem and let the computer, through the use of logic, solve it for us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to show how Prolog works, we aim to use it to represent the same problem and reasoning that Quark used to convince Sakonna. To do this first lets examine the situation depicted the episode a bit more closely. In the episode the Maquis are a group that are at odds Cardassian colonists both living the Demilitarized Zone. Tensions were escalating as the Cardassian colonists were recently supplied in secret with weapons by the Cardassian Union. As a result Sakonna, along with other members of the Maquis, aimed at acquiring more weapons of their own. Even after it was found that the Cardassian Union was behind weapon supplies, Sakonna still aimed at gathering more, as a way to ensure peace. Quark pointed out the flaws in the logic of her argument, given the Third Rule of Acquisition: &amp;quot;Never spend more for an acquisition than you have to.&amp;quot; If the goal of Sakonna is truly to acquire peace, than it is the perfect time to be negotiating with the Cardassian colonists. With the flow of the smuggled in weapons having stopped, and both sides already having weapons, neither the Maquis nor the Cardassian colonists have any advantage. By aiming to acquire weapons still, they would only escalate the conflict, and making peace more costly in the long run.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To express this scenario with Prolog, we are going to introduce some elements of this language first (for a bit more through introduction see the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.learnprolognow.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Learn Prolog Now!&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; available online). There are three basic elements to a Prolog program: facts, rules and queries. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facts are elements that have been stated to hold. For example the following statement:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;can be used to denote that the advantage is held by the Cardassians colonists.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules are a way for Prolog to infer new information from the knowledge that already exists. For example if we aim to state that &amp;quot;if the Cardassian colonists have the advantage the price of peace is high&amp;quot; in Prolog we would have the rule: &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(high) :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two parts to writing such rules in Prolog: the body and the head. The body of the rule is in this case &lt;code&gt;advantage(cardassians)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; while the head is &lt;code&gt;priceOfPeace(high)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. In Prolog if the body of the rule holds true, than it can be concluded that the head is true as well. This exactly matches to what we aim to express: if the Prolog program knows that the Cardassian colonists hold the advantage, than it can conclude that the price of peace is high. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facts and rules together form the knowledge base that can describe a domain. In this case the domain is the situation between the Cardassian colonists and the Maquis. The final piece, queries, allows us to examine this knowledge base and ask questions on what Prolog can infer from this knowledge. For the above example we could query whether the price of peace is indeed high, which should follow directly from the semantics of the rules and facts that we have described.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that we load in the knowledge base consisting of the above-mentioned fact and rule, the query: &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(high).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that asks whether the price of peace is high, will return &lt;code&gt;true&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; indicating that this is indeed the case. Instead if we ask whether the price of peace is low, using the query:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(low).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the result will be &lt;code&gt;false&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; indicating this is not the case.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also ask more open ended questions using variables. Variables are written by starting with a capitalized letter (or an underscore), such as &lt;code&gt;X&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. These variables could be used to write queries with unknowns. The query: &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will give us the result: &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;X = high
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which again is what would directly follow from the facts and the rules. What Prolog does with variables is to try to &amp;quot;unify&amp;quot; them with known values that match (or other variables). In this case from the knowledge base we have given it, it unifies it with the value of &lt;code&gt;high&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the basic elements of facts, rules and queries Prolog is able to represent and answer problems in many domains. This is also shows off the feature of a logical programming language, such as Prolog, that make it different compared to many other programming languages. Instead of telling the program what to do, the program becomes a description of the domain, over which queries are answered to solve the overall goal. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the above basics, Prolog has many features to support the description of more complicated domains. Here we only list a few that helps us to convey our translation of Quark&#x27;s reasoning into Prolog. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such feature is the use variables within the rules themselves. The rule &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;acquirePeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X) :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;indicates that the price of acquiring peace depends on the price of peace.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rule &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(low)  :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;shows off the logical operator &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, meaning that the price of peace is low if both the Cardassians and the Maquis have the advantage. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rule&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(low)  :- \+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians), \+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;shows off the logical &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, denoted by the &#x27;+&#x27; symbol, which states that the price of peace is also low if neither the Cardassians nor the Maquis have the advantage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, much like in other languages, comments for the code can also be written. This is done by prefacing a line with &amp;quot;%%&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if we put every element together to use Prolog to describe Quarks scenario, a possible knowledge base is as follows:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;%% Rules
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;acquirePeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X)  :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(low)  :- \+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians), \+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(low)  :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(high) :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(low) :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians)  :- &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;weapons&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians), \+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;weapons&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis)  :- \+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;weapons&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;weapons&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;%% Facts
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;weapons&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cardassians).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;weapons&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(maquis).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the overall knowledge base, the logic of Quark&#x27;s reasoning is broken down into a number of rules and a pair of facts. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules state that advantage of either side, the Cardassians settlers or the Maquis, is decided by one side having weapons while the other side has not. The price of peace is in turn dependent on who has the advantage. In this formalisation the price of peace is only high if Cardassians have the advantage. Finally the price of acquiring peace is dependent solely on the price of peace.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The facts for this scenario is that both the Cardassian settlers and the Maquis have weapons. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this knowledge base describing Quark&#x27;s reasoning process the query to see for what price we can aquire peace:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;acquirePeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will indeed return&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;X = low
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;indicating that acquiring peace can be done at a low price. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going a bit beyond this query, if we would further want to test the logic of Quark&#x27;s scenario, we can also inquire about other information.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example if we would ask for the price of peace:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;priceOfPeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we would also unsurprisingly get &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;X = low
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as with the rules defined in our knowledge base these values are intertwined. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also ask for who has the advantage:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;advantage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which will return: &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;false&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is completely in line with the scenario that noone has the advantage. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also ask who has weapons, the query of:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;weapons&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;gives us the answer&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;X = cardassians
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... but wait, this can not be right! Did we not state in the knowledge base that both the Cardassian colonists and the Maquis have weapons? Prolog can actually return mutliple answers, if they exist. In &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.swi-prolog.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;SWI-Prolog&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; this can be done by pressing semicolon (&lt;code&gt;;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) after an answer, in which case another answers is returned, if it exists or simply false otherwise. By pressing &lt;code&gt;;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; once after the first answer we will see a total output such as:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;X = cardassians &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;X = maquis.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully Sakonna would also be quite convinced with the logic of Prolog, but just to be absolutely sure, lets examine some scenario&#x27;s where the facts of the scenario are changed. In such cases the rules should still be applied in ways that we would expect.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose that our only fact now is that only the cardassians colonists have weapons, while rules remain the same. Giving the query for knowing the price of acquiring peace:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;?-  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;acquirePeace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(X).
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will now return:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;pro&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-pro &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-pro&quot; data-lang=&quot;pro&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;X = high 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, much like Quark&#x27;s application of the Third Rule of Acquisition, this intro would have been enough to convince Sakonna of the logic of purchasing peace at the lowest possible price. Similarly, I hope that as a reader, this article gave some insight to the usefulness of Prolog in such scenarios. Next time, you are dealing with a problem domain, that would easily match to a similar scenario of rules, facts and queries, give Prolog a try. It is, after all, a very logical choice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Excavating a Common Treasure</title>
		<published>2018-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2018-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/common-treasure/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://www.newresalhaider.com/post/common-treasure/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;History is full of legends of ancient treasures and powerful artifacts, lost to time or hidden by purpose, that would bring glory, power and riches to their discoverer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=centeredfig&gt;
    &lt;img src=winged-bull.jpg&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        
        &lt;h4&gt;A winged bull depicted on an on archaeological artifact from the Assyrian empire between 1400 and 1200 BC. Cylinder Seal with Winged Bull - Walters Art Museum Licensed under CC0.&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
        
        
    &lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;!-- {{&lt; figure src=&quot;&#x2F;img&#x2F;post&#x2F;2018&#x2F;common-treasure&#x2F;winged-bull.jpg&quot; title=&quot;A winged bull depicted on an on archaeological artifact from the Assyrian empire between 1400 and 1200 BC. Cylinder Seal with Winged Bull - Walters Art Museum Licensed under CC0.&quot; &gt;}} --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the history of software development is much shorter than the history of mankind, there already exists artifacts that have near mythological status when it comes to software development, yet often go hidden underneath the surface. One of these is the language of Common Lisp.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Lisp is a language originally from the early 80s, and was a standardization of many dialects of the Lisp programming language, which explains both the Common and Lisp part of the name. Lisp itself is one of the oldest general purpose programming languages, first specified in 1958. From Lisp many ideas that we consider common in other languages were popularized, such as conditionals (the &lt;code&gt;if and else&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; structure), notion of functions as first class elements, and many others (see this &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.paulgraham.com&#x2F;diff.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on more of these ideas). Common Lisp is also often &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gigamonkeys.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;introduction-why-lisp.html&quot;&gt;mentioned&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as an amazing and fun language to learn, which makes it the clear-cut choice for this article.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the story goes it gives the user untold levels of productivity and joy of development. One other big advantage is that Common Lisp used to be the language of A.I. research. There is lots of existing code out there for systems on the subject of knowledge representation, reasoning and planning. Given the resurgence of fields such as a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.w3.org&#x2F;standards&#x2F;semanticweb&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Semantic Web&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that make use of such A.I. systems, learning from such tools and techniques, or even using them directly, can be invaluable. In this post, I aim to find out a very small portion of the riches we can dig up using Common Lisp, and to share this experience with the reader. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=centeredfig&gt;
    &lt;img src=seal.jpg&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        
        &lt;h4&gt;Cylinder Seals were common objects that were used to designate ownership in ancient Mesopotamia. Although describing to a different notion of &amp;#x27;common&amp;#x27; these show remarkable of craftsmanship that we hope to introduce ourselves to in Common Lisp. Cylinder Seal with Two Heroes and a Tree - Walters Art Museum Licensed under CC0.&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
        
        
    &lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;!-- {{&lt; figure src=&quot;&#x2F;img&#x2F;post&#x2F;2018&#x2F;common-treasure&#x2F;seal.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Cylinder Seals were common objects that were used to designate ownership in ancient Mesopotamia. Although describing to a different notion of &#x27;common&#x27; these show remarkable of craftsmanship that we hope to introduce ourselves to in Common Lisp. Cylinder Seal with Two Heroes and a Tree - Walters Art Museum Licensed under CC0.&quot; &gt;}} --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add as a disclamer, I do have experience with a similar language, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that I use in my day-to-day programming, as well as with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gnu.org&#x2F;software&#x2F;emacs&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Emacs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (namely &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;spacemacs.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Spacemacs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), so I probably have some head start in using and editing the language. Nonethess I aim to make this introduction accessible to readers without such knowledge. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any treasure hunt, preparation is often key. As we are unfamiliar with the language itself it is good to read guides and tutorials to prepare. The guide to selecting the right equipment for our adventure is the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lispcookbook.github.io&#x2F;cl-cookbook&#x2F;getting-started.html&quot;&gt;cl-cookbook&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which describes how to get started with Common Lisp.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Lisp is a language with multiple implementations. As recommended by our guide we are using &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.sbcl.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Steel Bank Common Lisp (SBCL)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as distribution and using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;roswell&#x2F;roswell&#x2F;wiki&quot;&gt;Roswell&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to manage it. Alternatively a more straightforward install is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;portacle.github.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Portacle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that could be used.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next is testing whether our implementation is working. We run the ReadEvalPrint Loop (REPL), which in the case of Roswell can be done with the command &lt;code&gt;ros run&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. What the REPL allows us to do is interactively develop our code by reading our input, evaluating it and printing the results. This is one of the many features in programming that originated with Lisp, but has since made its way to many other languages. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the question is how we should write Common Lisp. One really nice resource for quickly familiarizing with new languages is Learn X in Y minutes, which also has a nice &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;learnxinyminutes.com&#x2F;docs&#x2F;common-lisp&#x2F;&quot;&gt;introduction to Common Lisp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. One of the most striking features of a Lisp, is the syntax of it. Elements are either atoms, that evaluate to themselves, such as the number &lt;code&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or s-expressions which are a list of expressions in brackets, such as &lt;code&gt;(+ 3 2)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Atoms evaluate to themselves, so if we write &lt;code&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; in the REPL, we get &lt;code&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; returned back. For s-expressions they are in the form of &lt;code&gt;(function param1 param2 ...)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, so in the case of &lt;code&gt;(+ 3 2)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; this will evaluate to &lt;code&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. One can of course nest these forms, for example &lt;code&gt;(+ 3 (+ 3 2))&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; will result in &lt;code&gt;8&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. In addition to functions there are macros available creating completely different forms to be translated into code. We will see some examples of this later in the article.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the REPL now working it is time to set up a project where we can write down all the code we need for our digging. According to our cookbook tutorial we can do this from the REPL, by getting &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;fukamachi&#x2F;cl-project&quot;&gt;cl-project&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and using it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(ql:quickload &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;cl-project&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(cl-project:make-project &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;#P&amp;quot;.&#x2F;common-treasure&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will give us the outline of project in the &lt;code&gt;common-treasure&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; directory. The files generated include a readme, systems for the project itself as well as tests and of course some skeletons for a test and a package itself respectively.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we are going to start off figuring out the package itself. Like in many other languages, functionality can be grouped together units, in this case packages. The generated file outline looks like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;defpackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; common-treasure
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (:use :cl))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;in-package&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; :common-treasure)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; blah blah blah.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the looks of it, it says to us that it defines a package named &lt;code&gt;common-treasure&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; using &lt;code&gt;:cl&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, which I assume is another package. There is also a call to &lt;code&gt;in-package&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; which looks like is there to ensure that everything else that follows is also in this package. Finally the &lt;code&gt;;; blah blah blah.&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; portion looks like a comment, something to describe functionality with, but nothing to be executed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in order to see if everything is working correctly let&#x27;s load this package. Instead of using the REPL from the command line, we are using it directly from our editor, in this case an &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gnu.org&#x2F;software&#x2F;emacs&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Emacs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; distribution named &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;spacemacs.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Spacemacs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Without going into much detail about Emacs it can be described as a highly configurable editor for pretty much any programming language out there. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;common-lisp.net&#x2F;project&#x2F;slime&#x2F;&quot;&gt;SLIME: The Superior Lisp Interaction Mode for Emacs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; ensures that our interaction with the REPL and the various language features go much more smoothly by integrating it with our editor of choice. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs is incredibly configurable, which is where Spacemacs comes in. It provides a set of curated configurations named layers, that make setting up the configuration for a particular language a breeze. We just enable the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;syl20bnr&#x2F;spacemacs&#x2F;tree&#x2F;master&#x2F;layers&#x2F;%2Blang&#x2F;common-lisp#install&quot;&gt;common-lisp layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of Spacemacs in the configuration file, add a small piece to let Emacs know of our Common Lisp distribution (see link), and we are good to go.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;!-- One really nice feature of Spacemacs is that commands can be executed and discovered by pressing the spacebar as the leader followed by some other combinations (this is where the distribution gets its name). For example, the process of starting SLIME can be done by navigating to a common lisp source file, such as that above, and pressing the keys `space m &#x27;` in succession. Note that this requires the use of [vi](https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Vi)-mode which is a whole another topic for discussion, but a more emacs like mode with a different leading key also exist. To keep things clear, regardless whichever mode or even emacs distribution one uses, I will try to name the command, and not the key combination whenever possible --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With everything setup now we can start our treasure hunt a bit more in earnest by starting SLIME. We are greeted by the message &amp;quot;Connected. Hack and be merry!&amp;quot; as well as a REPL in a window. Lets start to dig around by figuring out what exactly all the elements do. We can use the command &lt;code&gt;slime-describe-symbol&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to get some more information about &lt;code&gt;defpackage&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and what it does. This brings up some documentation on &lt;code&gt;defpackage&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. It shows us that this is a macro, as well as the various options one can use with it. A macro, without going into too much detail, is essentially a way to convert forms into different ones before evaluating them. We can get a bit more info on the workings by calling the command &lt;code&gt;slime-hyperspec-lookup&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. This takes us to the &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.lispworks.com&#x2F;documentation&#x2F;HyperSpec&#x2F;Front&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Common Lisp Hyperspec&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with more detailed docs. The pages for &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.lispworks.com&#x2F;documentation&#x2F;HyperSpec&#x2F;Body&#x2F;m_defpkg.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;defpackage&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.lispworks.com&#x2F;documentation&#x2F;HyperSpec&#x2F;Body&#x2F;m_in_pkg.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;inpackage&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; more or less confirm their use is as we expected.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it is time to start writing some new code. We remove the comments and create a function named &lt;code&gt;hello-treasure&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, that should just print the text &amp;quot;Hello Treasure&amp;quot;. We add the following to our file:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;defun &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;hello-treasure &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;print &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Hello Treasure!&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  )
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in place of the comments, and we run the command &lt;code&gt;slime-complile-and-load-file&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Compilation succeeds, but when we aim to call the function  &lt;code&gt;(common-treasure:hello-treasure)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; get an error when trying to call the function, saying &amp;quot;The symbol &amp;quot;HELLO TREASURE&amp;quot; is not external to the &amp;quot;COMMON TREASURE&amp;quot; package.&amp;quot;. This due to the fact that we did not declare the function external in the &lt;code&gt;defpackage&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; package declaration. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is really interesting is that, although we have this issue, instead of just failing the SLIME REPL presents us with a number of options. For example we can  &lt;code&gt;0: [Continue] Use symbol anyway.&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;1: [Retry] Retry SLIME REPL evaluation request.&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;2: [*Abort] Return to SLIME&#x27;s top level.&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. In this case we can just abort, and modify the package declaration, but it is interesting to be offered all these options.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By adding &lt;code&gt;(:export :hello-treasure)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;defpackage&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; macro, we can do another call and it indeed returns &amp;quot;Hello Treasure!&amp;quot; in the REPL.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we got the basics down we would like to have a slightly bigger example in which we make use of an existing library. While digging around for the software languages and libraries of the past is often the matter of some searching, reading, coding and a bit of trial and error. Digging around in the world is process governed by various regulations and laws. This is especially true in cities with long history, where a regular building site can easily unearth archaeological finds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=centeredfig&gt;
    &lt;img src=excavation-city.png&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        
        &lt;h4&gt;Digging in the certain urban areas can easily lead to excavations done before any subsequent work is done. Romano-Celtic temple excavated in London.&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
        
        
    &lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;!-- {{&lt; figure src=&quot;&#x2F;img&#x2F;post&#x2F;2018&#x2F;common-treasure&#x2F;excavation-city.png&quot; title=&quot;Digging in the certain urban areas can easily lead to excavations done before any subsequent work is done. Romano-Celtic temple excavated in London.&quot; &gt;}} --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, there are often a set of regulations that specify whether one can dig in areas of archaeological interests. As an example we use a portion of the rules by the municipality of Utrecht, as described on a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.utrecht.nl&#x2F;fileadmin&#x2F;uploads&#x2F;documenten&#x2F;9.digitaalloket&#x2F;REO&#x2F;archeologische-waardenkaart-2009.pdf&quot;&gt;map&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of Utrecht and surrounding areas (in Dutch).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These regulations can be summarized by a number of rules, based on two conditions: the type of area and the size of the area that is to be disturbed. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the area is of high archeological value, then a permit is required no matter what the size of the area is to be disturbed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the area is of high archeological expectation, then a permit is required when the size of the area that is to be disturbed is larger than 100m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the area is of archeological expectation, then a permit is required when the size of the area that is to be disturbed is larger than 1000m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such regulations can be encoded into a regular function that returns a true or false to the question &amp;quot;Is the a permit required?&amp;quot; based on two parameters, the size of the area and the type of the area. However this could be more complicated and harder to maintain if the set of regulations, along with conditions and outcomes, become more complex.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various approaches to deal with this issue. One of these is to encode the facts on which our answer relies into a knowledge base, and have a general mechanism to derive new knowledge from existing facts. This later process is often denoted as inferring or reasoning to derive new knowledge. Such an approach can make it easier to use and maintain such a system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this article we are going to implement such an approach using &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lisa.sourceforge.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LISA&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This is a production rule system, in which the knowledge base is encoded in a set of facts, and rules are uses as a way to derive new knowledge. It is easy to see how such a system would be a good fit for our problem: our domain restrictions are already formulated as a set of rules. It would also allow us to use some existing libraries, to see more of what Common Lisp has to offer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start off, first we need to add a dependency to LISA into our system. One of the files created by cl-project is an &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;common-lisp.net&#x2F;project&#x2F;asdf&#x2F;?&quot;&gt;asdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; file that describes how to build the software we are creating. Here we can add the dependency on Lisa, resulting in the following file:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;#|
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;  This file is a part of common-treasure project.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;|#
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defsystem &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;common-treasure&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :version &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0.1.0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :author &amp;quot;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :license &amp;quot;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :depends-on (&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;lisa&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; Here we add the dependency on LISA.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :components ((:module &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;src&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                :components
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                ((:file &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;common-treasure&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :description &amp;quot;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :long-description
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;#.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;read&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;-file-&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;string
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;     (subpathname *&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;load-pathname&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;* &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;README.markdown&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :in-order-&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;to &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((test-op (test-op &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;common-treasure-test&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we just need to make sure the dependencies needed are actually downloaded and available. For this we use &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.quicklisp.org&#x2F;beta&#x2F;&quot;&gt;quicklisp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which is the library manager Common Lisp. By using the command &lt;code&gt;(ql:quickload &amp;quot;common-treasure&amp;quot;)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; we can get all the dependencies for our system, which in this case consists of just LISA.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in order to translate our example scenario, we look at some of the examples that are available for LISA. A typical system consists of a knowledge base, in which facts are defined as &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.aiai.ed.ac.uk&#x2F;%7Ejeff&#x2F;clos-guide.html&quot;&gt;Common Lisp Object System (CLOS)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; objects and rules to manipulate such instances as the reasoning method. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CLOS is a way in which Common Lisp can do object-oriented programming, and LISA co-opts this as a way to represent facts in the knowledge base. Without going into detail on object-oriented programming theory, this allows one to, define classes, create instances of those classes and define methods that make use of those classes (see this &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.aiai.ed.ac.uk&#x2F;%7Ejeff&#x2F;clos-guide.html&quot;&gt;nice intro on Common Lisp Object System (CLOS)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for its general use). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of LISA, these allow us to represent classes of facts, specific instances of facts, and methods that can be used with those facts. For example we can represent the type of facts in our domain with two classes of objects: one that represents &amp;quot;area&amp;quot; and one that whether &amp;quot;a permit is required&amp;quot;. In Common Lisp these can be defined with the &lt;code&gt;defclass&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; macro. So for our example the following would be a call for permission requirement:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;defclass&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; permit-required ()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of the area, we need to represent two facts about it: what the archaeological type of it is, and what size of the area is disturbed. Such elements of the classes are described in CLOS using slots. There are many possible options that are available to describe a slot:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:initarg&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; describes the name of the slot.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:initform&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is the default value it is given initially.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:accessor&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; can be used to define a function for accessing the slot value.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting this together gives us the following class for representing the area:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;defclass&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; area ()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ((archeological-type :initarg :archeological-type :initform &amp;quot;&amp;quot; :accessor :archeological-type)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;   (size-disturbed :initarg :size-disturbed :initform &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; :accessor :size-disturbed)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we figured out how represent facts, we need to encode the rules of our domain into our system. We can do this with 3 rules that describe what to do in the cases of &lt;code&gt;high archeological value&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;high archeological expectation&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;archeological expectation&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules themselves described with three parts:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The antecedent, which is the set of conditions that have to be true. &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The arrow sign &lt;code&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; .&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consequent, which contains the facts that need to be derived or any actions that we want to perform. &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of LISA, and in many other rule based definitions, the antecedent and the consequent are also called Left Hand Side (LHS) and Right Hand Side (RHS), as they are respectively on the left and right hand side of the arrow. What exactly can be put into the LHS and RHS is dependent on the language for the rule definitions, but one standard way they are used is in the LHS the conditions are described based on the facts that could be in the knowledge base, and on the RHS facts are added in the knowledge based on the meaning of the rule. For example for one of our rules, if the know the fact that our area is of high archaeological value (LHS), we can derive the fact that we need a permit (RHS). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Describing our three rules this way in LISA looks as follows, using the &lt;code&gt;defrule&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; macro:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; If the area is of high archeological value, then a permit is required no matter what the size of the area is to be disturbed.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defrule high-value () (area (archeological-type &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;high-value&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;)) =&amp;gt; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;assert &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make-instance&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;#39;permit-required))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; If the area is of high archeological expectation, that a permit is required when the size of the area that is to be disturbed is larger than 100m&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;&#x2F;sup&amp;gt;.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defrule high-expectation () (area (archeological-type &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;high-expectation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;) (&amp;gt; size-disturbed &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))  =&amp;gt; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;assert &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make-instance&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;#39;permit-required))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; If the area if of archeological expectation, that a permit is required when the size of the area that is to be disturbed is larger than 1000m&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;&#x2F;sup&amp;gt;.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defrule expectation () (area (archeological-type &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;expectation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;) (&amp;gt; size-disturbed &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))  =&amp;gt; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;assert &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make-instance&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;#39;permit-required))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules are reasonably straightforward, in that they require the condition matching in the knowledge base, before they assert an instance of the &lt;code&gt;permit-required&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; fact into the knowledge base. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These together already describe the domain, but for this article we also show how things work with two examples. In one scenario we assert that we have an area with &lt;code&gt;high-value&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; archaeological type and a to be disturbed are with the size of 2000m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. In this case we would need a permit, due to our &lt;code&gt;high-value&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; rule. In the second scenario, the area is of &lt;code&gt;high-expectation&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; but the size of the area disturbed is only 10m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. In this case none our rules will fire, and no &lt;code&gt;permit-required&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; fact instance is put into the knowledge base.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executing the system is just a matter of adding these facts in the knowledge base and letting the system run. In LISA adding a fact can be done using &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; similarly to what the RHS of the rules are doing. To actually run the system, unsurprisingly, the function &lt;code&gt;run&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; can be called. To see what facts are in the knowledge base the function &lt;code&gt;facts&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; prints them out for us to see. To tie things together, we make sure that the knowledge base is reset before we execute anything using &lt;code&gt;reset&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the full example implementation that we put together:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;defpackage&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; common-treasure
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  )
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;in-package&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; :lisa-user)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(reset)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;defclass&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; area ()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ((archeological-type :initarg :archeological-type :initform &amp;quot;&amp;quot; :accessor :archeological-type)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;   (size-disturbed :initarg :size-disturbed :initform &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; :accessor :size-disturbed)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;defclass&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; permit-required ()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; If the area is of high archeological value, then a permit is required no matter what the size of the area is to be disturbed.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defrule high-value () (area (archeological-type &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;high-value&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;)) =&amp;gt; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;assert &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make-instance&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;#39;permit-required))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; If the area is of high archeological expectation, that a permit is required when the size of the area that is to be disturbed is larger than 100m&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;&#x2F;sup&amp;gt;.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defrule high-expectation () (area (archeological-type &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;high-expectation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;) (&amp;gt; size-disturbed &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))  =&amp;gt; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;assert &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make-instance&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;#39;permit-required))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; If the area if of archeological expectation, that a permit is required when the size of the area that is to be disturbed is larger than 1000m&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;&#x2F;sup&amp;gt;.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defrule expectation () (area (archeological-type &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;expectation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;) (&amp;gt; size-disturbed &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))  =&amp;gt; (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;assert &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make-instance&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;#39;permit-required))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;;Test fact 1
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;; (assert ((make-instance &amp;#39;area :archeological-type &amp;quot;high-value&amp;quot; :size-disturbed 2000)))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;;;Test fact 2
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;assert &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;((&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make-instance&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;#39;area :archeological-type &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;high-expectation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot; :size-disturbed &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;10&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(facts)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(run)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(facts)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that here the &lt;code&gt;fact 1&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is commented out, to test the assert of &lt;code&gt;fact 2&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, so that running the other scenario is just a matter of commenting and un-commenting the relevant lines. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first scenario, with fact 1, the output of our initial program is as follows:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[package common-treasure]#&amp;lt;INITIAL-FACT &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 0 {1002669853}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&amp;lt;AREA &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 1 {1002745373}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;For a total of 2 facts.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&amp;lt;INITIAL-FACT &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 0 {1002669853}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&amp;lt;AREA &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 1 {1002745373}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&amp;lt;PERMIT-REQUIRED &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 2 {100283A363}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;For a total of 3 facts.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that we print out our facts twice, once before the run and once after, but it shows that now the permit requirement was derived.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the case of using &lt;code&gt;fact 2&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; , we get the following output:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-lisp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lisp&quot; data-lang=&quot;lisp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[package common-treasure].#&amp;lt;INITIAL-FACT &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 0 {1004D40AB3}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&amp;lt;AREA &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 1 {10020107C3}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;For a total of 2 facts.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&amp;lt;INITIAL-FACT &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 0 {1004D40AB3}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;#&amp;lt;AREA &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;; id 1 {10020107C3}&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;For a total of 2 facts.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows that our fact base did not change due to our running the reasoning system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there we have it, a bit of a peek of what can be done with Common Lisp. I have to say the language and its various features are quite a bit daunting, as I feel I have only scratched the surface of what is possible, with both interacting with the language as well as with A.I. tools such as LISA. That said digging into the language and seeing how it can handle a small, but also relevant scenario, felt like a worthwhile journey, and that is an experience always worth treasuring.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Legal Regulatory Compliance Within The Financial Domain.</title>
		<published>2017-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2017-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/legal-banking-compliance/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://www.newresalhaider.com/project/legal-banking-compliance/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Regulatory compliance is the goal of an organization to ensure it complies with all the relevant policies, regulations and laws. Failure to comply can have grave consequences for an organization, with huge fines and penalties being imposed. Regulatory pressure has been increasing over the years, with new and more complex regulation being enacted. This is especially true for the financial sector, where in the wake of the financial crisis, new policies and laws where enacted, both internal and external, to prevent a similar crisis happening in the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These new and changing policies and laws give a huge challenge for financial organizations. These issues get compounded by fact that in a global world, internal, national and international regulations create an interwoven set of rules that need to be interpreted and applied on various financial products and services. Ensuring this compliance, is a time and expertise intensive task that often needs to be done manually. Automating these tasks is a huge challenge due to the fact that more traditional techniques are often ill equipped to tackle such an ever changing and complex domain in a way that is transparent to the domain experts and regulators.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, the goal is to find innovative techniques and solutions to the issue of regulatory compliance in the legal and financial domain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
