<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Law on Newres Al Haider</title>
    <link>/tags/law/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Law on Newres Al Haider</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Newres Al Haider</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/law/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Excavating a Common Treasure</title>
      <link>/post/common-treasure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/common-treasure/</guid>
      <description>History is full of legends of ancient treasures and powerful artifacts, lost to time or hidden by purpose, that would bring glory, power and riches to their discoverer.
  A winged bull depicted on an on archaeological artifact from the Assyrian empire between 1400 and 1200 BC. Cylinder Seal with Winged Bull - Walters Art Museum Licensed under CC0.   Although the history of software development is much shorter than the history of mankind, there already exists artifacts that have near mythological status when it comes to software development, yet often go hidden underneath the surface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legal Regulatory Compliance Within The Financial Domain.</title>
      <link>/project/legal-banking-compliance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/legal-banking-compliance/</guid>
      <description>Regulatory compliance is the goal of an organization to ensure it complies with all the relevant policies, regulations and laws. Failure to comply can have grave consequences for an organization, with huge fines and penalties being imposed. Regulatory pressure has been increasing over the years, with new and more complex regulation being enacted. This is especially true for the financial sector, where in the wake of the financial crisis, new policies and laws where enacted, both internal and external, to prevent a similar crisis happening in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>